Dungeon player strategy

One of Hero IK's particularities is the large gameplay difference between the adventurer player and dungeon player.

The adventurer player's gameplay is rather simple - the most important thing is knowing how to manage your mana properly. Like a good friend of mine says: "no mana, no goodies!". The rest is nothing more than a question of choice and combos between the player's adventurers and their equipment cards.

For the dungeon player, things are a bit harder. Generally, I'd say that four or five games are required as the dungeon player to start grasping the finesse required and the difficulties of the role.

The goal of this little strategy guide is to help you understand these aspects as quickly as possible.

To start, there's the most important thing: the construction phase!

The construction phase is very important. It's the cornerstone of the dungeon's defense. At first, it'll seem underwhelming, perhaps even useless, but without a good management of this phase, the dungeon player cannot win.

What to do during the construction phase?

During this phase, you will have to look at the cards on the top of each of the dungeon's pile and will get to switch two of these piles. And so, the first thing to do is to look at the visible (or hidden) monsters that the adventurers can face and guess at which one of them they will attack. You will need to anticipate the adventurer's movements to make the most of the next monster to show up. Being able to read the adventurers' intentions properly and strategically choosing which monster you use to protect yourself should give you a head start on your way to victory!

It is therefore very important to know the powers of the adventurers facing you, as this can also influence your construction phase.

A few things to do:

Always plan ahead to give a valid target to a "bodyguard" monster. Meaning, always be sure that there's a visible monster next to it, or even better, a Fierce monster! For instance, a visible bodyguard monster flanked by a greenskin and a trap would be an ideal target for the adventurers, since the Tenacity token is useless on a greenskin (since battles with them is resolved through a Rock-Paper-Scisors match)... And traps can't benefit from Tenacity tokens.

Delay the arrival of a psi monster if the adventurers have little or no mana. There are few psi monsters - use them well and they will enable you to win many games.

Do a "lock-out" once in a while, when the adventurers are low on mana but still have a large amount of courage tokens. To do a "lock-out", bring out three monsters with a value higher than the adventurers can reach in a battle unless they use mana at the same time. In some dungeons, most notably the Den of Dementia, the lock-out can happen quite often.

Think about the bonuses! Always make the right monsters benefit from the right bonuses. And the greenskins are rather good at that.

Here's an example of a possible situation in the Lair of the Lich dungeon:

There are two greenskins visible. The first one grants a +1 to Undead, the second gives +1 to Nemesis. Cinders (Undead Nemesis) shows up on top of a pile and the adventurer player has been avoiding greenskins for the past few turns as he's running low on courage tokens. You could say he now fears greenskins. Place Cinders on the pile where the greenskins aren't, and whaddaya know, he gets a +2 bonus just for showing up. Furthermore, the best thing to do in this example would be to make Cinders face-down in order to for the adventurers to take the bluff and end up in a very difficult combat.

Lack or surplus of mana! The adventurers are in good shape, overflowing with mana? Now's the time to give them as much as possible - they'll surely leave a small mana-giving monster (I call those "walking potions") for later, and that's perfect. Put behind it a monster without mana and flood the other corridors with mana monsters. Don't forget that 50% of the dungeon cards give mana - if they waste too many when they don't need any, they'll run out by the end.

And inversely, if the adventurers have little or no mana left, again, out-think them by anticipating their next battle and put a mana monster behind a mana-less dungeon card.

Lack of a dungeon card type: imagine a group of three adventurers who are lacking two blue dungeon cards to call upon an Ultimate power. Well, it's up to you to place those blue cards behind a dangerous monster, to bring them out face down, to put a Tenacity token on them, etc... You can delay the use of an ultimate power with proper management of the construction phase – always keep an eye on how many cards the adventurers need to call upon their Ultimate power.

Being able to anticipate the adventurers' moves is, as you can see, very important for the dungeon player!

But don't forget you can bluff, too...

And to bluff, nothing beats the ambush! When a new dungeon card is placed in front of the adventurer player (after the elimination of the last one), the dungeon master can choose to put it in play face-down by spending 1 Fear token. Although usable only during the combat phase, this power is very versatile.

At first glance, one could think that the idea is to hide all the powerful monsters in order to trap the adventurers. But that doesn't work all that often, and the adventurers can often be wary of such a trick... On the other hand, there are many pleasant ways of using this power.

A group of weakened adventurers will hesitate against facing a hidden monster, on the off chance that they'd have to face an overly powerful monster, so take advantage of that to hide a weak mana-giving monster.

Also, hide greenskins once in a while, when adventurers are low on courage and it could be a fatal encounter for them.

But most importantly, when you hide a card - it is automatically immune to all powers which may target a face-up, visible, dungeon card, as in the case of Nem Akh's Ultimate power.

The management of fear tokens is important: you don't have a lot of them and you need to make every one of them count. Wait for your Fierce monsters, hide your monsters when the destructive ultimate powers are about to be called, force the adventurers to reroll a combat die which could cost them a lot.

Gameplay for the dungeon player is a lot of anticipation, a bit of bluff and having nerves of steel.

Don't take combat against greenskins lightly, as they're indeed the only fights in which adventurers can't interfere using their mana or their Skills (with the exception of one very precise case). And so, by the end of the dungeon, you should often see weakened adventurers take on a strong dragon as a preferred target over a poor little goblin!

And so this short list of tips ends, but not without a quick reminder: anticipate, anticipate, anticipate and never forget the construction phase.

Good luck!

STRATÉGIE DU JOUEUR DONJON

Une aide de jeu d'Emmanuel Beltrando

Une des particularités dé Hero IK est la grosse différence de gameplay entre le joueur aventurier et le joueur donjon. Le gameplay du joueur aventurier est plutôt simple. Le plus important est de savoir qu'il faut bien gérer sa mana. Comme le dit un bon ami à moi : "pas de mana, pas de chocolat". Le reste n'est qu'une question de choix et de combo entre ses aventuriers et ses cartes équipement. Pour le joueur donjon, c'est un peu plus dur. De façon générale, j'ai tendance à dire qu'il faut 4 à 5 parties en tant que joueur donjon pour commencer à entrevoir les finesses et les difficultés de ce rôle.

Le but de ce petit guide stratégique est de vous aider à appréhender ces aspect le plus vite possible.

LA PHASE DE CONSTRUCTION

La phase de construction est très importante, C'est la clé de voûte de la défense du donjon. Au début. elle vous semblera déroutante voire peut-être inutile, mais sans une bonne gestion de cette phase, Le joueur donjon ne peut pas gagner.

Que faire pendant la phase de construction ?

Pendant cette phase, vous allez regarder les cartes au sommet de chaque paquet du donjon et vous allez inverser 2 de ces paquets. Donc, la première chose à faire est de regarder les monstres visibles (ou cachés) que les aventuriers peuvent affronter et deviner lesquels les aventuriers vont attaquer. Il faut anticiper le mouvement des aventuriers pour préparer au mieux le prochain monstre qui se présentera. Une bonne anticipation des aventuriers et un bon choix stratégique sur le monstre à placer derrière vous emmènera beaucoup de victoire !

Il est donc bien important de connaître les pouvoirs des aventuriers en face, cela peut influencer votre phase de construction.

L'ANTICIPATION DES MONSTRES

Toujours anticiper une cible valide pour un monstre « garde du corps», c'est-à-dire, toujours être sûr qu'il a à côté de lui un monstre face visible, voire un monstre hargneux ! En effet un monstre garde du corps face visible avec à ses côtés un peau verte et un piège sera de toute évidence une cible parfaite pour les aventuriers, car Le bonus du jeton de ténacité +1 ne sert a rien sur une peau verte où les combats se font à Pierre Feuille Ciseaux... Et les pièges n'ont pas droit aux jetons de ténacité.

Regardez l'arrivée d'un monstre psi, si les aventuriers ont pas où peu de mana. Il y a peu de monstres psi, utilisez-les bien et ils vous feront gagner beaucoup de parties.

LA TACTIQUE DU LOCK

Tentez le lock, à certains moments, alors que les aventuriers sont faibles en mana mais encore avec beaucoup de points de courage. Tentez le lock, faites arriver de front 3 monstres avec une valeur supérieure au nombre maximum qu'ils peuvent atteindre en combat sans mana. Dans certains donjons, notamment celui de l'Antre de la Folie, le lock peut arriver très souvent.

LA GESTION DES BONUS

Pensez au bonus ! Faites toujours profiter des bons bonus aux bons monstres. Et à ce jeu là les peaux vertes ne sont vraiment pas mal.

Exemple d'une situation possible dans le donjon du Repaire de la Liche :

Il y a deux peaux-vertes faces visibles. Le premier donne +1 aux morts-vivants, le second donne +1 aux Némésis, Cendres (Némésis Mort-Vivant) se présente au sommet d'un paquet et le joueur évite les peaux-vertes durant quelques tours car il lui reste peu de point de courage. Il craint maintenant les peaux vertes. Placez Cendres dans le tas où il n'y a pas les 2 peaux vertes, et hop en arrivant dl bénéficie d'un bonus de +2. Le must dans cet exemple est même de faire arriver Cendres face cachée afin de très certainement proposer un combat difficile aux aventuriers.

LA PÉNURIE

La pénurie ou surplus de mana !

Les aventuriers sont en pleine forme. ils débordent de mana de tous les côtés, c'est donc le moment de leur en donner le plus possible. Ils vont très certainement laisser de côté un petit monstre à mana (j'appelle ça une « potion sur patte ») pour plus tard, tant mieux. Placez derrière lui un monstre sans mana et abreuvez à volonté les autres couloirs de monstres à mana. N'oubliez pas que 50% des cartes donjon donnent de la mana: s'ils en consomment trop maintenant, ils en manqueront vers la fin. A contrario, si les aventuriers ont peu où plus du tout de mana, encore une fois anticipez leur prochains combats et placez derrière celui-ci une carte donjon sans mana.

La pénurie d’un type de carte de donjon.

Imaginez un groupe de 3 aventuriers à qui il manque 2 cartes donjon bleu pour faire un pouvoir ultime. Hé bien, à vous de les placer derrière un monstre difficile, de les faire tenir face cachée, de leur mettre des jetons tenace, etc... Vous pouvez retarder 1e pouvoir ultime avec une bonne gestion de phase de construction, pensez à toujours regarder combien il manque de cartes aux aventuriers pour faire leur pouvoir ultime. Anticiper est donc très important pour le donjon !

LE BLUFF

Pour le bluff rien de mieux que l'embuscade !!! Lorsqu'une nouvelle carte donjon est placée devant le joueur aventurier (après l'élimination de la précédente), le maître du donjon peut choisir de la placer face cachée en dépensant 1 jeton de Peur. Utilisable uniquement durant la phase de combat. Ce pouvoir est très versatile.

De premier abord, on a tendance à croire qu'il s'agit de cacher tous les monstres très forts afin de piéger les aventuriers. Mais cela ne marche pas souvent et les aventuriers peuvent régulièrement se méfier de cela... Mais il y a bien des façons agréables de jouer ce pouvoir. Un groupe d'aventuriers affaiblit hésitera à attaquer une carte cachée de peur d'affronter un monstre trop fort, profitez-en alors pour y cacher un monstre faible donnant de la mana. Cachez également de temps à autres des peaux-vertes, lorsque les aventuriers seront bas en courage. Cela pourra être fatal.

Mais le plus important, lorsque vous cachez une carte : elle est automatiquement immunisée à tous les pouvoirs qui ciblent une carte donjon face visible, comme par exemple le pouvoir ultime de Nem Akh.

LES JETONS DES PEUR

La gestion des jetons de peur est importante : vous n'en avez pas beaucoup et il faut les dépenser au plus juste : attendez vos monstres hargneux, cachez vos monstres au moment où les pouvoirs ultimes de destruction arrivent, faites relancer un dé de combat qui peut coûter très cher aux aventuriers.

ULTIMES CONSEILS

Le jeu du joueur donjon, c'est beaucoup d'anticipation, un peu de Bluff et pas mal de sang-froid. Ne prenez pas à la légère les combats contre les  peaux-vertes, c'est en effet les seuls combats où les aventuriers ne peuvent pas interagir avec leur mana et les dons (sauf cas très précis). Et vous verrez souvent en fin de partie que les aventuriers affaiblis préfèrent attaquer un gros dragon plutôt qu'un pauvre gobelin !

Donc voila, un dernier peut rappel: anticipez, anticipez, anticipez et n'oubliez jamais la phase de construction.

Bonne chance !!